<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A true and exact copie of Mr. Love's speech and prayer, immediately before his death, on the scaffold at Tower-Hill, Aug. 22. 1651.</title>
            <author>Love, Christopher, 1618-1651.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1651</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A88595</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L3181</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E790_4</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R3848</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872506</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872506</idno>
            <idno type="VID">167574</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A88595)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 167574)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 120:E790[4])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A true and exact copie of Mr. Love's speech and prayer, immediately before his death, on the scaffold at Tower-Hill, Aug. 22. 1651.</title>
                  <author>Love, Christopher, 1618-1651.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Published for the use of Mr Love's special friends.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1651]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing; publisher's statement from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "printed 2d Septemb: 1651".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Love, Christopher, 1618-1651.</term>
               <term>Last words --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:167574:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A true and exact Copie of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>
               </hi> Love'<hi>s Speech and Prayer, immediatly before his Death, on the Scaffold at Tower-Hill,</hi> Aug. 22. 1651.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved Chriſtians,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am made this day a ſpectacle unto God, Angels and Men: and among Men I am made a grief to the Godly, a laughingſtock to the wicked, and a gazingſtock to all; yet bleſſed be my God, not a terrour to my ſelf. Although there be but little between me and death, yet this bears up my heart, there is but little between me and Heaven. It comforted D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Taylor</hi> the Martyr, when he was going to Execution, that there were but two ſtyles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween him and his Fathers Houſe; There is a leſſer way between me and my Fathers Houſe, but two ſteps between me and Glory; it is but lying down upon the Block, and I ſhall aſcend upon a Throne. I am this day ſayling towards the Ocean of Eternity, through a rough paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to my Haven of Reſt; through a Red Sea to the Promiſed Land. Methinks I hear God ſay to me as he did to <hi>Moſes, Go up to Mount Nebo and die there:</hi> So to me, Go up to <hi>Tower-Hill,</hi> and die there. <hi>Iſaac</hi> ſaid of himſelf, that he was old, and yet he <hi>knew not the day of his death;</hi> but I cannot ſay ſo, I am young, and yet I know the day of my death, and I know the kinde of my death, and the place of my death alſo. I am put to ſuch a kinde of death as two famous Preachers of the Goſpel were put to before me, <hi>John</hi> the Baptiſt, and <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle, they were both beheaded; you have mention of the one in Scripture-ſtory, and of the other in Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall Hiſtory. And I read in <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4. the Saints were <hi>beheaded for the Word of God, and for the teſtimony of Jeſus:</hi> But herein is the diſadvantage which I lie under in the thoughts of many; they judge that I ſuffer not for the Word of God, or for Conſcience, but for medling with State-matters. To this I ſhall briefly ſay, That it is an old guiſe of the devil, to impute the Cauſe of Gods peoples ſufferings, to be contrivements againſt the State, when in truth it is their Religion and Conſcience they are perſecuted for: The Rulers of <hi>Iſrael</hi> would have put <hi>Jeremy</hi> to death upon a Civil Account, though indeed it was only the truth of his Prophecy that made the Rulers angry with him; and yet upon a Civil Account they pretend he muſt die, becauſe he fell away to the <hi>Caldcans,</hi> and would have brought in forreign Forces to invade them: The ſame thing is laid to my charge, of which I am as innocent as <hi>Jeremy</hi> was. Yea I finde other inſtances in Scripture, wherein the cauſe of the Saints ſufferings were ſtill imputed to their medling with State matters: <hi>Paul</hi> who did but preach Jeſus Chriſt, yet he muſt die, if the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple might have their will, under pretence that he was a mover of ſedition. Upon a Civil Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count my life is pretended to be taken away, whereas indeed it is, becauſe I purſue my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and will not proſtitute my Principles and Conſcience to the Ambition and luſts of men. Beloved, I am this day making a double exchange, I am changing a Pulpit for a Scaffold, and a Scaffold for a Throne; and I might adde a third, I am changing this numerous multitude, the preſence of this numerous multitude on <hi>Tower-Hill,</hi> for the innumerable company of Saints and Angels in Heaven the holy hill of <hi>Sion;</hi> and I am changing a Guard of Souldiers for a Guard of Angels, which will receive me, and carry me into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome. This Scaffold it is the beſt Pulpit that ever I preached in; in my Church-Pulpit, God through his grace made me an Inſtrument to bring others to Heaven; but in this Pulpit he will bring me to Heaven, Theſe are the laſt words that I ſhall ſpeak in this world, and it may be I ſhall bring more glory to God by this one Speech on a Scaffold, then I have done by many Sermons in a Pulpit.</p>
            <p>Before I lay down my Neck upon the Block I ſhall lay open my Cauſe unto the People that hear me this day, that I might not die under all that obloquy and reproach that is caſt upon me; and in doing it I ſhall avoid all rancor, all bitterneſſe of ſpirit, animoſity and revenge; God is my Record, whom I ſerve in the ſpirit, I ſpeak the truth and lye not; I do not bring a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vengefull Heart unto the Scaffold. This day, before I came here, upon my bended knees I have begg'd mercy for them that denied mercy to me, and I have prayed God to forgive them who would not forgive me, I have forgiven from my Heart the worſt enemy I have in all the world; and this is the worſt that I wiſh to my Accuſers and proſecutors who have purſued my bloud, that I might meet their Souls in Heaven.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:167574:2"/>
            <p>I ſhall divide my Speech into three parts: I ſhall ſpeak ſomething concerning my Charge, and a word concerning my Accuſers and touching my Judges, without any Animoſity at all; and then ſomething concerning my Self for my own Vindication; and then a word of Exhortation, and ſo I ſhall commit my Soul to God.</p>
            <p>Concerning my Charge, it is black and hideous, many things falſly ſuggeſted, hardly a line of it true, and nothing Capitall ſufficiently proved againſt me by any one Act that I am conſcious to my ſelf I did. The Charge is high and full, but the Proof empty and low; though there were eight Witneſſes that came in againſt me, yet none of them did prove that ever I writ any Letter, or directed any man to write a Letter into <hi>Scotland,</hi> or into forreign parts; No man did prove that. I ſent away any Letter, that I received any Letter, that I collected, or gave, or lent any Money to aſſiſt or promote the Scottiſh Warre: This is all that is ſworn againſt me, that I was preſent where Letters were read, and that I made a motion for Money to give to <hi>Maſſey;</hi> ſo that (beloved) my preſence at, and concealment of Letters that were received and ſent from forreign parts, is that for which I muſt die.</p>
            <p>As concerning my Accuſers I ſhall not ſay much; I do forgive them with all my heart, and I pray God forgive them alſo. Yet what the Evangeliſt ſaid concerning Chriſt's Accuſers, I may, without vanity or falſhood ſay of mine, That they did not agree amongſt themſelves: One Witneſſe ſwears one thing, and another the quite contrary: Yea not only did they contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict one another, but ſometimes a ſingle Witneſſe contradicted himſelf. And though their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony did condemn my Perſon, yet I have condemned their Teſtimony. And truly there are many remarkable circumſtances that I might take notice of, either in, or before, or ſince the Trial that might be worthy obſervation, but I will not inſiſt upon it; only in the general (for I ſhall name none of my Accuſers) ſome of them have ſent to me, to pray me to forgive them the wrong they have done me: And one of them hath written to me under his own hand, to pray me to forgive him the wrong that he hath done me; and told me withall, that that day I ſhould die a violent death, his life would be no comfort to him, becauſe he was an Inſtrument in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away of mine. Others of the Witneſſes were, ſome terrified before they would teſtifie; ſome were hired, ſome fined before they would bear Witneſſe againſt me. But I will be off of this. As concerning my Judges, I will not judge them, and yet I will not juſtifie them: I will ſay but this of them, I beleeve that what moved <hi>Herod</hi> to cut off <hi>John</hi> Baptiſt's Head, that moved them to cut off mine; and that was for his Oaths ſake: <hi>Herod</hi> to avoid Perjury would commit Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; whereas if <hi>John</hi>'s Head had been upon his Shoulders, he would have been guilty of neither.</p>
            <p>I have ſomething in the ſecond place to ſpeak concerning my Self, and then I ſhall come briefly to a concluſion. Concerning my Self, I have gone through various reports; there are many ſons of Slander whoſe mouthes are as open Sepulchres, in which they would bury my Name, before my Friends can bury my Body; but my comfort is, there will be a Reſurrection of Names as well as Bodies at the laſt day: God will not only wipe off all tears from my eyes this day, but he will alſo wipe off all blots and reproaches from my Name before many daies be over; and though my body will ſoon rot under ground, yet my hope is, my Name will not rot above it. I am not ignorant what Calumnies are caſt upon me, and more likely to be after I am dead and gone. The very night before my intended Execution the laſt Moneth, there was an inſulting Letter written to me, to tell me, that after my death there ſhould be ſomething pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſht againſt me to my ſhame. I hope you will have ſo much charity, as not to beleeve reproaches caſt upon a dead man, who will be ſilent in the grave, and not able to ſpeak a word in his own Juſtification. I am aſperſed both as to my Practice, and as to my Principles. I ſhall begin with the firſt. There are five aſperſions as to my Practice that are laid upon me, That I am a Liar, That I am an Extortioner, That I am an Adulterer, That I am a Murtherer, and That I am a Turbulent Perſon: Crimes ſcandalous in any man, but much more abominable in a Miniſter. Now I hope you will beleeve a dying man, who dares not look God in the face with a lie in his mouth: I am accuſed of lying, that what I denied before the High Court of Juſtice, that afterwards I ſhould confeſſe, or elſe was proved againſt me. Now in the preſence of God I tell you, as I would confeſſe nothing that was Criminal, ſo I did deny nothing that was true; and that I may ſeal it to you with my bloud, the ſame Proteſtations I made before the High Court, I ſhall make briefly now: 1. That I never writ Letter to the King, Queen, Church or State of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or to any particular perſon of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation ſince the Warres began to this
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:167574:2"/>day. 2. That I never received any Letter writ to me, either from the King, or from the Queen, or from the Church or State of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or from any particular perſon of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation, ſince the Warres began to this day. 3. That I never collected, gave or lent one Peny of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, either to the King, Queen, Church or State of <hi>Scotland,</hi> or to any particular perſon to ſend into <hi>Scotland</hi> to any perſon of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation to this day. It is true, I did confeſſe, though it was not proved (and haply upon that ground the miſtake might ariſe) I did give Money to <hi>Maſsey,</hi> and I did alſo write a Letter to him, but he is of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> not of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation. That for which I come here is only for moving for Money for him, and that not upon a Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary account, but meerly to relieve his Perſonal neceſſities, and for being preſent where Letters were read from him and others. And although Man hath condemned me, yet I am ſo far from thinking that either God or my own Conſcience condemns me, as Sinning in what I am con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned for, that both God and my own Conſcience doth Acquit me: And what I ſaid at the Barre when I received my Sentence, that I ſhall ſay upon the Scaffold, That for thoſe things for which I am condemned, neither God nor my own Conſcience condemns me.</p>
            <p>Again, I am accuſed to be an Extortioner; and this is in the mouths—I am loth to name them, becauſe I will avoid all rancour: But I am charged as if I ſhould be a grievous Extorti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oner to receive Thirty pounds for the Loan of Three hundred pounds, Beſides Eight pounds <hi>per centum</hi> for Intereſt; which in the preſence of God and of you all I do declare to you is a moſt notorious and abominable falſhood.</p>
            <p>I am accuſed likewiſe to be an Adulterer, and this report is not in the mouths of mean men, but in the mouths of thoſe that ſit at the Stern: As if I were a debauched Perſon, and were guilty of Uncleanneſſe. Now I tell you, as <hi>Luther</hi> ſaid of himſelf in another caſe, That he was not tempted to Coveteouſneſſe; ſo through the grace of God I can ſay, I have not been tempted in all my life to Uncleanneſs. It doth not much grieve me though theſe Slanders be caſt upon me: I know my betters have been worſe accuſed before me: <hi>Athanaſius</hi> was accuſed by two Harlots that he had committed Folly with them, and yet the man was Chaſt and innocent. <hi>Beza</hi> was charged, not only with Drunkenneſſe, but with Laſciviouſneſſe alſo, and many others have been accuſed with the ſame, if not with worſe Slanders then I have been.</p>
            <p>But (that which goeth neareſt my heart) I am accuſed to be a Murtherer alſo; and this is a Charge high indeed: I am charged with the guilt of all the Bloud of <hi>Scotland;</hi> whereas did I lye under the guilt of one drop of Bloud, I could not look upon God with ſo Chearfull a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and I could not be filled with ſo Peaceable a Heart and Conſcience as I have at this day. I bleſſe my God I am free from the Bloud of all men: Thoſe who lay this to my Charge, they do to me as <hi>Nero</hi> did to the Chriſtians, He ſet <hi>Rome</hi> on fire and then charged the Chriſtians with it: So they put <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland</hi> into a Flame, and yet Charge me with the guilt of that Bloud, who have poured forth Tears to God night and day, to quench the Burning which theſe mens Ambitions and Luſts have kindled: And I would fain know of any man, what Act is it that I have done? or what is it that was proved in the High Court againſt me, that makes me guilty of <hi>Scotlands</hi> Bloud? Did I ever invite the <hi>Scots</hi> to invade <hi>England?</hi> What man doth lay that to my Charge? Did I ever incourage the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army to invade <hi>Scotland?</hi> What Action is it that I have done that makes me guilty of that Bloud? Indeed this I have done, and this I have and this I do ſtand to; I have as a private man prayed unto God many a day, and kept many a Faſt, wherein I have ſought God that there might be an Agreement between the King and the <hi>Scots,</hi> upon the Intereſt of Religion and Tearms of the Covenant: Now, by what conſequence can this be ſtrained, to Charge me with <hi>Scotlands</hi> Bloud? For my part, I was but only at one Meeting where the queſtion was propoſed (Faſts only excepted) What ſhould be thought fit to be done to promote the Agreement between the King and the <hi>cots?</hi> and that was moved in my Houſe: And to that end when there were ſome things there propoſed, which they call'd A Commiſſion or Inſtructions to ſend to <hi>Holland,</hi> as ſoon as ever I heard them, I did declare againſt them. I did declare that it was an Act of high Preſumption for private perſons to Commiſſionate; and an Act of notorious Falſhood to ſay it was in the name of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian Party, when none knew of it (that I know of) but only thoſe few then preſent. Now this is only a politicall Engine to make the Presbyterian Party odious, who are the beſt friends to a well-ordered Government, of any ſort of people in the world.</p>
            <p>I am accuſed likewiſe to be a man of a Turbulent ſpirit, to be an enemy to the peace and quiet of the Nation. Now, as to this, let my Congregation and my Domeſtical relations
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:167574:3"/>judge for me, whether I am not a man that would fain have lived quiet in the Land: I am as <hi>Jeremy</hi> was, <hi>Born a man of contention;</hi> not Actively, I contend, I ſtrive with none: But Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively, many ſtrive and contend with me. God is my Witneſſe, My Judgement hath put me upon endeavouring after all Honourable and Juſt waies for Peace and Love among the Godly. The grief of my heart hath been for the Diviſions, and the deſire of my Soul for an Union among God's People. When I ſpeak of an Union I would not be miſunderſtood, I do not mean a State-union, to Ingage to the preſent power, that is againſt my Principles; That is to ſay <hi>A Confederacy with them that ſay A Confederacy:</hi> That is rather a Combination then a Goſpel-union: O join not with them leaſt ye be conſumed in their ſins; They who get Power into their hands by Policy, and uſe it with Cruelty, will loſe it with Ignominy. It was ſaid of Pope <hi>Boniface,</hi> He did enter into the Popedom like a Fox, reign'd like a Lion, but died like a Dog. Beloved, the Union for which I plead is a Church-union; to wit, Love among the Godly, for this the deſires of my Soul have ever been, That thoſe that fear God might walk hand in hand in the Fellowſhip of the Goſpel, both in Truth and Love: If this Union be not, I am afraid, through our Diviſions, a company of looſe Libertines will ariſe, who will endeavour, not only to overthrow the Doctrine of Faith, and the power of Godlineſſe, but even Good manners alſo. I remember an Obſervation of holy <hi>Greenham's,</hi> Giving his judgement upon the ſtate of <hi>England,</hi> he ſaid, There is great fear that Popery is coming into <hi>England,</hi> and I fear it too; but (ſaies he) I fear more the coming of Atheiſm into <hi>England,</hi> then the coming in of Popery; and truly that is my fear alſo. Thus as to my Practice: A word now as to my Principles.</p>
            <p>I am accuſed to be an Apoſtate, to be a Turn-coat, to be this, to be that, to be any thing but what I am: In the general I will tell you, I bleſſe my God, A High Court, a Long Sword, a Bloudy Scaffold hath not made me, in the leaſt, to alter my Principles, or to wrong my Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence: And that I might diſcover to you my Principles, I hope I ſhall do it with Freedom; I will irritate and provoke none, what I ſhall ſay ſhall not be an irritation or provocation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, at leaſt not intended by me; but only as a genuine and clear manifeſtation of my own Principles, how they ſtand.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, My Principles as to Civil and Religious Affairs, I do declare that I dye with my judgement ſet againſt Malignity, I do hate both name and thing; I ſtill retain as vehement a deteſtation of a Malignant Intereſt as ever I did; yet I would not be miſ-underſtood: I do not underſtand nor count the Godly Party, our Covenanting Brethren in <hi>Scotland</hi> to be a Malignant Party; nor the <hi>Scots</hi> defending their Nation and Title of their King, to be a Malignant Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, but an honeſt and juſtifiable Cauſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Though I am againſt Malignity, yet I am not againſt but for a regulated Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, A mixt Monarchy, ſuch as ours is I judge to be the beſt Government in the world: I did, its true, in my Place and Calling oppoſe the Forces of the late King, but I was never againſt the Office; I am not only againſt Court Paraſites, who would ſcrew up Monarchy into Tyranny, but againſt thoſe who pull down Monarchy to bring in Anarchy.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I was never for putting the King to death, whoſe Perſon I did promiſe in my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to preſerve: It is true, I did in my Place and Calling oppoſe his Forces, but I did never endeavour to deſtroy his Perſon. There is a ſcandal rais'd of me, that in a Sermon at <hi>Windſor</hi> I ſhould have theſe words; that <hi>It would never be well with</hi> England <hi>till the King were let bloud in the Neck-vein;</hi> which ſpeech I utterly deteſt, Profeſſing, as a dying man, in the preſence of God and of you all, I never ſpake ſuch words, as relating to him: Though my judgement was for bringing Malignants, who did ſeduce him and draw him from his Parliament, to condign pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment; yet I deem'd it an ill way to cure the Body Politick, by cutting off the Political Head.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, I dye with my judgement abſolutely ſet againſt the Ingagement; I pray God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give them that impoſe and ſubſcribe it, and preſerve thoſe that refuſe it.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, I would not in the next place be lookt upon, now I am a dying man, as a man own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this preſent Government; I dye with my Judgement againſt it: It is true, in a caſe of Life I did Petition the preſent Power, and did give them the Titles they take to themſelves, and that others give them; but herein I did not wrong nor thwart my Principles. There are many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances in Scripture to juſtifie this: <hi>Huſhai</hi> did give the Title of King to <hi>Abſolom,</hi> though <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolom</hi> had no right to that Title, for <hi>David</hi> was the lawfull King: And <hi>David</hi> himſelf gave him that Title as well as <hi>Huſhai.</hi> And <hi>Calvin</hi> he gave the Title to the <hi>French</hi> King, calling him the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:167574:3"/>moſt Chriſtian King, yet we know he was a Papiſt: And we give a Title to King <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth, and call him the Defender of the Faith, and yet he had no right to that Title, for he was an Oppoſer not a Defender of the Faith; that Title was given him upon an evill ground, becauſe he oppoſed the Faith; he oppoſed the doctrine of <hi>Luther,</hi> therefore the Pope gave him that Title, <hi>The Defender of the Faith:</hi> and yet none did ſcruple to give him that Title that was then commonly given him.</p>
            <p>Sixthly, In the next place I diſcover my judgement (I provoke none, only tell you what my own thoughts are, that ſo after I am dead and gone I might not be belied, for I dare not now belie my Principtes) My judgement is againſt the Invaſion of the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Nation by the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army. They, who gave us a friendly aſſiſtance, who are joyned with us in the ſame Covenant, who drew a ſword with us in the ſame Quarrell; ſhould I live a Thouſand years, I ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver draw ſword againſt them; But the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Army have forgot the Brotherly Covenant: So that <hi>Scotland</hi> may ſay as <hi>Edom, The men of my Confederacy, who were at peace with me, have riſen up and prevailed against me;</hi> Becauſe <hi>Scotland</hi> will not be a Common-wealth they ſhall not be a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; becauſe they will not break Covenant, ſome men would have them broken; becauſe they will not lay their Conſciences waſte, their Land muſt be laid waſte.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, (and ſo I have done, only with a word of Exhortation,) I die cleaving to all thoſe Oaths, Vows, Covenants and Proteſtations that were impoſed by the two Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, as owning them, and dying with my Judgement for them; To the Proteſtation, the Vow and Covenant, the Solemn League and Covenant. And this I tell you all, I had rather dye a Covenant-keeper, then live a Covenant-breaker.</p>
            <p>I am now come to the third and laſt part of my Speech, and ſo I ſhall have done, and commit my ſoul to God who gave it. My Exhortation firſt ſhall be to this great City, Unto the godly Miniſtry of it; and unto my own Congregation, from whom death parts me, which nothing elſe could.</p>
            <p>To the City I wiſh an Affluence and Confluence of all bleſſings upon it; and yet I fear gray hairs, as the ſad ſymptoms of a declenſion, are here and there upon <hi>London,</hi> and yet ſhe knows it not. O <hi>London, London,</hi> God is ſtaining the pride of all thy Glory. Thy Glory is flying away like a Bird; Contempt of the Miniſtry, oppoſition againſt Reformation, Generall Apoſtaſie, Covenant-breaking hath brought <hi>London</hi> low, and I fear will yet bring it lower; I tremble to think what evils are coming upon it: This City it is the receptacle of all Errors; that as your Commodities are vented and ſpread from hence into every corner of the Land, ſo have Hereſies and Blaſphemies had their firſt riſe from this great and populous City, and from hence are ſpread into all Countries.</p>
            <p>To the Inhabitants of this City I commend but theſe few particulars. Firſt, Let me beg you to love your Painfull and your Godly Miniſters: If they be taken away you are like to have worſe come in their rooms. I know the Presbyterian Miniſters are the great eye-ſore, who have formerly been counted the Chariots and Horſe-men of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> But I will ſay of <hi>London</hi> (as was ſaid of <hi>Leyden, That after</hi> Junius <hi>an Orthodox Miniſter was taken away,</hi> Arminius <hi>that peſtilent Heretick came in his room.</hi>) If your Godly Miniſters (and there have been ten already at one blow taken from you) if they be taken away, <hi>Arminians, Anabaptiſts,</hi> nay Jeſuites are likely to ſupply their rooms, if God in mercy prevent not.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Submit your ſelves to Church-Government, that would lay a curb and reſtraint upon your luſts; it is a Golden and an Eaſie yoak, to which if you do not ſubmit, God may lay a Heavy and an Iron yoak upon your necks.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Take heed of thoſe Doctrines that come under the notion of <hi>New-light;</hi> thoſe doctrines you ought to ſuſpect, whether true, which the broachers of them ſay are New; for truth is as old as the Bible: A remarkable paſſage I would ſuggeſt unto you, in the 32 of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> and the 17. it is ſaid there, <hi>they choſe them New Gods that were Newly come up,</hi> and what were theſe New Gods? the next words tell you, they were old devils; for they ſacrificed to devils and not to God; now their ſacrificing to old devils, it is called a ſacrificing (to deceive the people) to new Gods, that were newly come up; yet their new Gods were but old devils; Why, ſo I ſay, though many things go under the notion of <hi>New-light,</hi> yet they are but old darkneſs, old Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies raked out of the dunghill, and which were buried in former ages of the Church, with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt and reproach many hundred years agoe.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Bewail your great loſs which you have in the taking away of ſo many Miniſters out
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:167574:4"/>of your City; there are ten Miniſters (if I miſtake not) that have been taken away and remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved at one blow, who were burning and ſhining lights in their ſeverall Candleſticks, and bright Stars in their ſeverall Orbs; Though I am not worthy of the world, and therefore am taken out of it, yet as for my ſuffering Brethren, who are now in bonds and baniſhment, the world is not worthy of them.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Again in the next place, Take heed of engaging in a Warre againſt your Brethren of the Scottiſh Nation, for my part I have oppoſed the Tyranny of a King, but I never oppoſed the Title — Take heed what you do —</p>
            <p>I have ſomething in the next place to ſpeak to the Godly Miniſtry of this City: Were it not that I am a dying man, I would not ſpeak to ſuch Reverend and Grave men, I would ſay as <hi>Elihu</hi> did (being but a young man,) Multitude of years ſhould teach wiſedome, and I would hold my tongue; but the words of a dying man take, whether they be diſcreet or no, or ſo well ordered or managed or no; as to them, I would firſt deſire God to ſhew them mercy, who have begged mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy for me; now at the day of my death I would begge but this of them; that, as they have not been aſhamed of my Chain, ſo they would now wax confident by my Bonds and by my Bloud; I know they are maligned and threatned, yet my praier for them is that in the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> 
               <hi>Act.</hi> 29. <hi>And now O Lord behold their threatnings, and grant that thy Servants may preach thy Word with all boldneſſe;</hi> Though I am but young, yet I will offer my young experience to my Grave Fathers and Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and that is this; Now I am to die, I have abundance of peace in my own Conſcience, that I have ſet my ſelf againſt the Sins and Apoſtacies of this preſent Age. It is true, my faithfulneſs hath procured me ill-will from men, but it hath purchaſed me peace with God; I have lived in peace, and I ſhall die in peace: That which I have to beſeech of the Miniſters is this, to beg them to keep up Church-Government; whatever God doth with the Governments of the world, turning Kingdoms upſide down, yet the Government of the Church ſhall ſtand; and of all Governments, I die with this perſwaſion, that the Presbyterial Government makes moſt for pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and for unity throughout the Churches of the Saints. I would begge them therefore to keep up Church-Government, that they would not let their Elderſhips fall, that they would take heed of too generall Admiſſions to the Lords Supper, that they be not too prodigall of the bloud of Chriſt, by too generall admiſſions of men to the Supper of the Lord, that ſealing Ordinance: And now I am ſpeaking to them, I ſhall ſpeak a word of them, and ſo I have done: I have heard many clamors ſince I came to priſon, as if all the City-Miniſters were engaged in the Plot (as it's called) that I am condemned for: now as a dying man, I tell you, that all the Miniſters that were preſent at the meetings, and had a hand in the buſineſſe, for which I am to be put to death, are either in priſon, or they are diſcovered already; and therefore I do here upon my death, free the Miniſters of the City, who are not yet in trouble, nor diſcovered to the Committee of Examinations, none of them had a hand in the buſineſſe in which I was engaged, in which my Conſcience tels me I have not ſinn'd. I have done immediatly, for I would fain be at my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Houſe.</p>
            <p>I have but a word to ſpeak to my own Congregation; I return praiſes unto God and thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fullneſſe unto them for the love I have had from them; I found them a ſolid, judicious, and many of them a religious people: the Miniſtry of that Learned man M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Anthony Burgeſs</hi> did much good amongſt them, though I have cauſe to be humbled that my weak Miniſtry did but little; They afforded me a great deal of love, and a liberall maintenance; And this is all I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fire of them, that they would chuſe a Godly, Learned, and Orthodox Miniſter to ſucceed, ſuch an one as may keep up and carry on Church-Government: It would be a great comfort to me before I go to Heaven, if I had but this perſwaſion, that a Learned, Orthodox, Godly man ſhould fill that Pulpit: and for encouragement to any godly Miniſter, whoſe lot may be to ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed me, I will ſay this, that he will have as comfortable a Livelihood, and as loving a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as are any people in <hi>London,</hi> a few only excepted: I had as much ſatisfaction among them as ever I had in any condition in all my life, and ſhould never have parted from them, had not death now parted us, to which I do ſubmit with all Chriſtian meekneſſe and chearfullneſſe. I am now drawing to an end of my Speech, and to an end of my life together: But before I do expire my laſt breath, I ſhall deſire to juſtifie God and to condemn my ſelf in all that is brought upon me; Here I come to that which you call an untimely end, and a ſhamefull death, but (bleſſed be God) it is my glory, and it is my comfort: I ſhall juſtifie God, he is righteous, becauſe I have ſinned; he is righteous, though he cut me off in the midſt of my
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:167574:4"/>daies, and in the midſt of my Miniſtry: I cannot complain that Complaint in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 44.12. <hi>Thou ſelleſt thy people for nought, and doſt not encreaſe thy wealth by their price:</hi> My bloud it ſhall not be ſpilt for nought, I may do more good by my death then by my life, and glorifie God more in dying upon a Scaffold, then if I had died of a diſeaſe upon my bed: I bleſſe my God I have not the leaſt trouble upon my ſpirit; but I do with as much quietneſſe of minde lie down (I hope I ſhall) upon the Block, as if I were going to lie down upon my Bed to take my reſt; I ſee men hunger after my fleſh, and thirſt after my Bloud, let them have it, it will haſten my happineſſe, and their ruine, and greaten their guiltineſſe: though I am a man of an obſcure Family, of mean Parentage, ſo that my bloud is not as the bloud of Nobles, yet I will ſay, it is a Chriſtians bloud, a Miniſters bloud, yea, it is innocent bloud alſo: My bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, my dead body, it will be a morſell, which I beleeve will hardly be digeſted, and my bloud it will be bad food for this Infant-Commonwealth (as M. <hi>Prideaux</hi> called it) to ſuck upon: Mine is not Malignant bloud, though here I am brought as a grievous and notorious offender. Now beloved, I ſhall not only juſtifie God (as I do,) without a complement, for he were very juſt, if my Priſon had been Hell, and this Scaffold the bottomleſſe pit, I have deſerved both; ſo that I do not only juſtifie God, but I deſire this day to magnifie God, to magnifie the riches of his glorious grace, that ſuch an one as I, born in an obſcure Countrey (in <hi>Wales.</hi>) of obſcure Parents, that God ſhould look upon me, and ſingle me out from amongſt all my kindred to be an object of his everlaſting love: that whenas the firſt fourteen years of my life I never heard a Sermon, yet in the fifteenth year of my life, God (through his grace) did convert me. And here I ſpeak it without vanity, (for what ſhould a dying man be proud of?) though I am accuſed of many ſcandalous evils, yet (I ſpeak to the praiſe and glory of my God) for theſe twenty years God hath kept me, that I have not fallen into any ſcandalous ſin: I have laboured to keep a good conſcience from my youth up, I magnifie his grace, that he hath not only made me a Chriſtian, but a Miniſter, and judged me faithfull to put me into the Miniſtry: And though the Office be trodden upon and diſgraced, yet it is my glory that I die a deſpiſed Miniſter; I had rather be a Preacher in a Pulpit, then a Prince upon a Throne; I had rather be an Inſtrument to bring ſouls to Heaven, then to have all the Nations bring in Tribute to me: I am not only a Chriſtian and a Preacher, but whatever men judge, I am a Martyr too, I ſpeak it without vanity; would I have renounced my Covenant, and debaucht my Conſcience, and ventured my ſoul, there might have been hopes of ſaving my life, that I ſhould not have come to this place; but bleſſed be my God I have made the beſt choice, I have choſen affliction rather then ſin, and therefore welcome Scaffold, and welcome Axe, and welcome Block, and welcome Death, and welcome All, becauſe it will ſend me to my Fathers Houſe: I have great cauſe to magnifie Gods grace, that he hath ſtood by me, during mine impriſonment, it hath been a time of no little temptation to me, yet (bleſſed be his grace;) He hath ſtood by me, and ſtrengthned me; I magnifie his grace, that though now I come to die a violent death, yet that death is not a terrour to me; through the bloud of ſprinkling the fear of death is taken out of my heart; God is not a terrour to me, therefore death is not dreadfull to me; I bleſſe my God, I ſpeak it without vanity, I have formerly had more fear in the drawing of a tooth, then now I have at the cutting off my head: I was for ſome: five or ſix years under a ſpirit of bondage, and did fear Death exceedingly, but when the fear of Death was upon me, Death was not near me, but now Death is near me, the fear of it is far from me: and bleſſed be my Saviour that hath the ſting of Death in his own ſides, and ſo makes the grave a bed of reſt to me, and makes Death (the laſt enemy) to be a friend, though he be a grim friend. Further, I bleſſe my God, that though men have judged me to be caſt out of the world, yet that God hath not caſt me out of the hearts and praiers of his people; I had rather be caſt out of the world, then caſt out of the hearts of godly men. Some think me (it is true) not worthy to live, and yet others judge I do not deſerve to die, but God will judge all, I will judge no man.</p>
            <p>I have now done, I have no more to ſay, but to deſire the help of all your praiers, that God would give me the continuance and ſupply of divine grace to carry me through this great work that I am now about; that as I am to do a work I never did, ſo I may have a ſtrength I never had: That I may put off this body with as much quietneſſe and comfort of minde, as ever I put off my clothes to go to bed; And now I am to commend my ſoul to God, and to receive my fatall blow, I am comforted in this, <hi>Though men kill me, they cannot damn me, and though they thruſt me out of the world, yet they cannot ſhut me out of heaven.</hi> I am now going to my long
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:167574:5"/>home, and you are going to your ſhort homes, but I will tell you, I ſhall be at home before you, I ſhall be at heaven my Fathers Houſe, before you will be at your own houſes: I am now going to the heavenly <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to the innumerable company of Angels, to Jeſus the Mediator of the New Covenant, to the ſpirits of juſt men made perfect, and to God the Judge of all, <hi>In whoſe preſence there is fulneſse of joy, and at whoſe right hand there are pleaſures for evermore:</hi> I conclude with the Speech of the Apoſtle, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.6, 7. <hi>I am now to be offered up, and the time of my depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is at hand; I have finiſhed my courſe, I have fought the good fight, I have kept the faith, Hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth there is a Crown of righteouſneſse laid up for me, and not for me only, but for all them that love the appearing of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> through whoſe bloud (when my bloud is ſhed) I expect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins and eternal ſalvation: And ſo the Lord bleſſe you all.</p>
            <p>Beloved, I will but pray a little while with you to commend my ſoul to God, and I have done.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <p>
               <hi>MOſt glorious and eternal Majeſty, thou art righteous and holy in all thou doſt to the Sons of men, though thou haſt ſuffered men to condemn thy Servant, thy Servant will not condemn thee. He juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies thee though thou cut'ſt him off in the midſt of his daies, and in the midſt of his Ministry, bleſſing thy glorious Name that though he be taken away from the Land of the Living, yet he is not blotted out of the Book of the Living: Father, my hour is come, thy poor Creature can ſay without vanity and falſhood, He hath deſired to glorifie thee on Earth, glorifie thou now him in Heaven; He hath deſired to bring the ſouls of other men to Heaven, let his ſoul be brought to Heaven. O thou bleſsed God, whom thy Creature hath ſerved, who hath made thee his hope, and his confidence from his youth: Forſake him not now he is draw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nigh to thee: Now he is in the valley of the ſhadow of death, Lord, be thou life to him: Smile thou up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him whilest men frown upon him: Lord, thou haſt ſetled this perſwaſion in his heart, that as ſoon as ever the blow is given to divide his head from his body, he ſhall be united to his Head in Heaven; bleſsed be God that thy Servant dies in thoſe hopes; bleſsed be God that thou haſt fill'd the ſoul of thy Servant with joy and peace in believing. O Lord, think upon that poor Brother of mine, that is a Companion in tribulation with me, who is this day to loſe his life as well as I; O fill him full of the joys of the holy Ghoſt, when he is to give up the ghoſt. Lord, ſtrengthen our hearts that we may give up the ghoſt with joy and not with grief. We intreat thee, O Lord, think upon thy poor Churches; O that</hi> England <hi>might live in thy ſight! and O that</hi> London <hi>might be a faithfull City to thee! that righteouſneſſe might be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them! that ſo peace and plenty might be within their wals, and proſperity within their habitations: Lord, heal the breaches of theſe Nations, make</hi> England <hi>and</hi> Scotland <hi>as one ſtaff in the Lords hand, that</hi> Ephraim <hi>may not envy</hi> Judah, <hi>nor</hi> Judah <hi>vex</hi> Ephraim, <hi>but that both may fly upon the ſhoulders of the</hi> Philiſtims: <hi>Oh that men of the Proteſtant Religion, engaged in the ſame cauſe and Covenant, might not delight to spill each others bloud, but might engage againſt the common Adverſaries of our Religion and Liberty! God ſhew mercy to all that fear him; the Lord think upon our Covenant-keeping Brethren of the Kingdom of</hi> Scotland, <hi>keep them faithfull to thee, and let not them that have invaded them, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpread their whole Land: Prevent the ſhedding of more Christian bloud, if it ſeem good in thine eyes. God ſhew mercy to thy poor Servant who is here now giving up the ghost: O bleſsed Jeſus, apply thy bloud, not only for my Juſtification unto life, but alſo for my comfort for the quieting of my ſoul, that ſo I may be in the joys of Heaven, before I come to a poſſeſſion of Heaven. Hear the prayers of all thy people that have been made for thy Servant; and though thou haſt denied prayer as to that particular requeſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning my life, yet let herein the fruit of prayer be ſeen, that thou wilt bear up my heart againſt the fear of death. God ſhew mercy to all that fear him, and ſhew mercy to all who have ingaged for the life of thy Servant; Let them have mercy at the day of their appearing before Jeſus Chriſt. Preſerve thou a Godly Miniſtry in this Nation, and reſtore a Godly Magiſtracy, and cauſe yet good daies to be the heritage of thy people for the Lords ſake. Now Lord, into thy hands thy Servant commits his Spirit, and though he may not with</hi> Stephen <hi>ſee the Heavens open, yet let him have the Heavens open; and though he may not ſee upon a Scaffold the Son of God ſtanding at the right hand of God, yet let him come to the glorious body of Jeſus Chriſt, and this hour have an intellectuall ſight of the glorious body of his Saviour. Lord Jeſus receive my Spirit, and Lord Jeſus ſtand by me thy dying Servant, who hath endeavoured in his life time to ſtand for thee: Lord hear, pardon all infirmities, waſh away his iniquity by the blood of Chriſt, wipe off re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaches from his Name, wipe off guilt from his Perſon, and receive him pure, and ſpotleſſe, and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe before thee in love. And all this we beg for the ſake of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Amen and Amen.</p>
            <p>The laſt words that he was heard to ſpeak were, <hi>Bleſsed be God for Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_note">
            <p>Publiſhed for the uſe of M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Love's</hi> ſpecial friends.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
